<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A letter from the King of Poland to his Queen in which is many particulars relating to the victories obtained against the Turks; with a prayer of the Turks against the Christians. Translated from the Cologn Gazett, Octob. 19. 1683,</title>
            <author>John III Sobieski, King of Poland, 1629-1696.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1683</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 8 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 3 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A46644</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing J449</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R218508</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99830093</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99830093</idno>
            <idno type="VID">34543</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A46644)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 34543)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2032:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A letter from the King of Poland to his Queen in which is many particulars relating to the victories obtained against the Turks; with a prayer of the Turks against the Christians. Translated from the Cologn Gazett, Octob. 19. 1683,</title>
                  <author>John III Sobieski, King of Poland, 1629-1696.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>4 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Dublin :</pubPlace>
                  <date>reprinted M. DC. LXXXIII. [1683]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>German original not traced.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Trinity College Library, Dublin.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Turco-Polish Wars, 1683-1699 --  History --  Sources --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Poland --  History --  John III Sobieski --  1674-1696 --  Sources --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:34543:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 16 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:34543:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 16 -->
            <p>A LETTER FROM THE KING of POLAND To His QUEEN; In which is Many Particulars relating to the VICTORIES Obtained againſt the Turks; WITH A Prayer of the TURKS Againſt The CHRISTIANS.</p>
            <p>Tranſlated from the Cologn Gazett, <hi>OCTOB.</hi> 19. 1683,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>D<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>BLIN,</hi> Reprinted M.DC.LXXXIII.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:34543:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 17 -->
            <head>A Letter from the King of Poland, to his Queen, in which is incerted many particulars relating to the Victories obtained againſt the Turks &amp;c.</head>
            <p>THe Immortal God to whom honour and Glory be aſcribed for ever has bleſt us with ſo ſignal a victory as ſcarce the memory of man can equal. The enemy was not only content to raiſe the ſeige of <hi>Vienna</hi> and leave us maſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of the field, But alſo of all their Cannon and Tents with ineſtimable treaſure and climbed over mountains of carcaſes made by their own bodys in the flight my eyes were never bleſt before with ſo delightful a proſpect as to ſee my Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers follow here a great drove of their ſheep and oxen and ther's a much great<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>er herd of Turkiſh Captives, nor my Ears charmed with ſo pleaſing muſick, as the howlings and dying groans of theſe miſerable wretches, ſo great was their haſt that the Prime <hi>Viſier</hi> almoſt alone and forſaken of all was forct with out the ceremony of his Turband to take his flight, But yet he left me Heir to to his tent, and riches which were ſhown by a Renegado of his own Retinue,</p>
            <p>I have preſented the Turkiſh Standard to his holineſs who was inſtrumental no leſs by his money, then his prayers, to their overthrow, the Prime <hi>Viſiers</hi> hors with all his trapings, I reſerved for my ſelf. And tho he was ſo fortunate in his flight to eſcape us, yet his Caymeram or Lievtenant General with ſome of his moſt conſiderable Baſſas fell by our ſwords, But the approaching night put a ſtop to our purſuit and their ſlaughter, thoſe <hi>Janazeries</hi> which were left behind in the Mines and Trenches we thought not worth the dulling of our ſwords therefore we made but one funeral Pile for them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> all and burnt them.</p>
            <p>In that Action there were about thirty thouſand Turks killed, beſides Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars, and 100000 Tents taken. Our Souldiers, and the Burghers of <hi>Vienna</hi> were two whole nights, and one day in Rifling their Tents and Bodies; and I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve a week would ſcarce ſuffice to finiſh it.</p>
            <p>The rarities which were found in the Prime <hi>Viſiers</hi> tent were no leſs nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous then ſtrange and ſurprizing, as very curious Parets and ſome birds of pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radice with all his Baners and fountains, and ſome Oſtriges which he choſe ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to kill then let them fall alive into our hands nay his diſpair and Jelouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sy tranſported him ſo far as to deſtroy his very Women for the ſame reaſon.</p>
            <p>The whole Army attributes the glory of this victory to God and us, and all the princes of the Empire with the great officers as the <hi>Duke</hi> of <hi>Bavarea</hi> and Lorrain, Prince Waldock &amp;c. were ſo far tranſported with my valour and ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs that their thanks and praiſes were more numerous then was their fears be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and Count <hi>Staremberg</hi> the Governor ſaluted me with the title of his migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty deliverer the common people in my going to and from the Churches Paid their veneration even to my very garments and and made their crys and accla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:34543:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 17 -->
reach the sky, of long live the King of <hi>Poland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the Battle we loſt ſome of our Friends as Prince <hi>Halicki</hi> and the Treaſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of our Houſhold, the Reverend <hi>Marinus Daniano</hi> heapt on me his prayers and blesſings and told me he ſaw a white Dove flutring over the Army which i<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> lookt upon as an happy Augure of our Victory.</p>
            <p>We are now on our march towards <hi>Hungary</hi> taking the advantage of their diſtraction, to defeat the remainder of their ſcattered troops and ſurprize <hi>Gran<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> or <hi>New-h<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uſel.</hi> I have all the Princes of the Empire my Companions in this En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprize who tell me they are ready to follow ſuch a Leader, not only into <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gary,</hi> but to the end of the <hi>World.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Prime <hi>Vizier</hi> being unable to put a ſtop to their purſuit told his Eldeſt Son <hi>Mahomet Han,</hi> that he muſt now bid adieu to all his Greatneſs, and never expect to be in ſaftey whilſt there lyes one ſtone upon another in the wals of <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enna.</hi> But withal bid him haſten to the <hi>Grand-Seignior</hi> and demand a ſpeedy ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour, to whom his Son replyed that he knew him too well for that, and there was nothing for them now to rely on but their flight.</p>
            <p>I am juſt now a going to take Hors and all my way for two Hungarian miles together are ſo ſtrewed with the carcaſes of men, horſes and camels that the ſtench of them would be inſupportable to any but a Souldier.</p>
            <p>I have ſent ſeveral diſpatches to forreign princes to give notice of this action, but the King of France was forgotten.</p>
            <p>I rejoyce to ſee our ſon <hi>Alexander</hi> of ſo clear and undaunted Courage who al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways ſtuck to me in my moſt iminent dangers and made the firſt onſet on a body of <hi>Turkiſh Spalies</hi> with that courage that he put them ſoon to flight and received the applauſe of the whole Army, He has contracted a very intimate friendſhip with the Young Duke of <hi>Bavaria</hi> with whom he equally divided the ſpoyl, this Prince has been very asſidious in his ſervices to me therefore I have preſented him 3 of my horſes, the Baſſa of Egypts tent and ſtandars, and ten pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of cannon, to his ſiſter the Dauphineſs a Locket of Diamond yet there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains ſuch heaps of their colours and ſemiters in our poſſesſion as are not to be numbred.</p>
            <p>All my country men marcht with the ſame bravely to the relief of <hi>Vienna.</hi> a<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the ſouldiers of Godfrey of Bullein did to the Holy land, and the miraculou<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> croſs that you preſented me with which was his companion in that expedition<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> I believe contributed no leſs to our victory.</p>
            <p>Thanks be to heaven now the half moon Triumphs no longer o'r the croſs and twas thrown down from St, Stephens ſteeple in <hi>Vienna</hi> whom had ore top<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſo long, imediatly on the defeat, Neither have the <hi>Turks</hi> any occaſion to upbraid us with their blaſphemous Mahometans proverb. Ye chriſtians where is your God.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:34543:3"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 18 -->
            <head>The Turks Prayer againſt the Chriſtians.</head>
            <p>ETernal God and Creator of all things and thou O <hi>Mahomet</hi> his Sacred and Divine Prophet we beſeech thee ſet us not dread the Chriſtians, who are mean and ſilly to rely on a Crucifyed <hi>God:</hi> By the power of thy right hand ſo ſtrengthen ours that we may ſurround this fooliſh people on every ſide &amp; ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly deſtroy them, at length fullfil our prayers and put theſe Miſcreants into our hands that we eſtabliſh thy throne for ever in <hi>Mecha</hi> and ſacrifice all thoſe Enemies of our Moſt holy Religion at thy Tomb, Blow us with thy Mighty breath like ſwarms of flies into their quarters and let the eyes of theſe Infidels be dazelled with the Luſter of our <hi>Moons,</hi> Conſume them with thy fiery darts &amp; blind them with the duſt which they themſelves have raiſed: Deſtroy them all in thine Anger, break all their bones in pieces, and conſume the fleſh and blood of thoſe who deſpiſe thy Sacrifice and hang the Sacred light of Circumciſion on the Croſs,, waſh them with ſhowers of many waters, who are ſo ſtupid to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip Gods they know not and make their <hi>Chriſt</hi> a Son to that God who never begot him. Haſten therfore their deſtruction we humbly entreat thee and blot out their Name and Religion, which they glory ſomuch in, from off the face of the Earth, that they may be no more, who contemn and mock at thy Law.</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:34543:3"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 18 -->
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
